<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="https://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Solarpunk Blue</title>
    <description>To imagine a more equitable and sustainable world</description>
    <link>https://solarpunk.blue/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://solarpunk.blue/feed/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2022 19:54:07 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2022 19:54:07 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Solarpunk 2050</title>
          
          <author>solarpunk.blue@gmail.com (Solarpunk Blue)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;I recently read Bill Gates’ book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/books/2021/feb/17/how-to-avoid-a-climate-disaster-by-bill-gates-review-why-science-isnt-enough&quot;&gt;How to Avoid a Climate Disaster&lt;/a&gt;. While I have a huge problem with the book’s philosophy&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, I have taken one thing away from it in this blog’s approach to advocating for a socialist revolution: work backwards from a goal and a long-term horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know many people want a socialist revolution &lt;strong&gt;now&lt;/strong&gt;, and they are working toward that goal either through political process or through yelling at other people on twitter.  Sadly, I am one small person with limited ability to effect massive changes, and realizing that, I’ve decided to take a different approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m issuing the #solarpunk2050 challenge.  A call to specifically articulate your best case scenario for an ecosocialist utopia by the year 2050&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, to invision the systemic changes that will need to take place for that outcome, and to prioritizing taking the smartest actions today to maximize the likelihood of that happening.  Some would call it incrementalist, but I, personally, see it as revolutionary—just over a longer timescale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-case-for-working-backwards&quot;&gt;The case for working backwards&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gates’ emphasized an interesting point when discussing how to evalutate different strategies for reaching net-zero carbon emissions by 2050. On the one hand, you can pursue a set of policies that can bring the largest drops in carbon emissions by 2030, but which might jeopardize the ability to get larger reductions by 2050.  Or on the other hand, you can pursue a set of policies that are much more likely to bring even greater reductions by 2050, but which may rely on delaying implementation after 2030 to avoid implementing something that sets back the long-term goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an even more extreme example, you might consider how can I reduce carbon emissions as much as possible this year, but this might actually have a backfire effect over the longterm.   In the specific case of climate change, reducing emissions a little bit over the short term isn’t helpful if it messes up with reaching net-zero over the long term.  Therefore, you wouldn’t want to pursue a strategy that emphasizes short term gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can look at a lot of things in this same light.  And in particular, I want to approach the construction of a sustainable, human-centered society in this way.  To do this, I’m going to work backwards from where I imagine the world could be, and give myself a suitable time-horizon to make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge is to break a solarpunk revolution down into 3 parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) what would define success,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) what big systemic changes need to take place to allow that success to happen, and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) what do I do today and every day, for the next year, and 28 years from now to make that change happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-would-define-a-solarpunk-revolution&quot;&gt;What would define a solarpunk revolution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For climate change, Gates’ easily identifiable goal was carbon neutrality.  For an equitable and sustainable world, the endpoint is harder to identify.  There are competing issues that need to be rectified, and, honestly, it isn’t up solely to me to identify what those are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, for articulating my own plan of action, I need to pick some endpoint that I think matches with the ideals that I think satisfy my fundamental principles of equity and sustainability. My four points to define a successful solarpunk revolution are as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) No one consuming more than a sustainable share of Earth’s natural resources, and society collectively preserving the ecological abundance of our planet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Increased standard of living so everyone on Earth is living with stability and dignity (at least $30/day in 2022 dollars)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Acknowledgement of a fundamental right to an equal share in both political and economic decision making&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) That the above be both objectively true and perceived as true by almost all of the population&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;socialism-in-28-years-broken-down&quot;&gt;Socialism in 28 years, broken down&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are the big society wide shifts that would have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it comes on three fronts: culture shift, economic shift, and electoral politics shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;culture-shift&quot;&gt;Culture shift&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the absolute most necessary change for creating a socialist society is the ongoing cultural shift towards collectivist morals.  Ultimately, I don’t believe there can be any change without a shift in people’s values underneath.  In fact, I think that the backlash to change is even more pronounced when someone tries to make change prior to the underlying cultural shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how do you take action for a culture shift?  It seems like culture shifts are assumed to be organic changes, but I believe there is a way to impact culture even if it’s slow moving.  There are two core parts to this: change the focus of conversation to shift the Overton window, and shift social status from capitalist values to egalitarian ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;shift-the-conversation&quot;&gt;Shift the conversation&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an idea of what is “acceptable” to talk about in polite society called the Overton window. The idea is that certain things are considered very mainstream, certain things are on the edges of the mainstream but still “normal,” and certain ideas fall outside in the “fringe.” Shifting the Overton window means shifting what falls directly inside the mainstream and bringing things that are fringe into the edge of the mainstream.  The most important thing about this theory is that it assumes since we are highly social that what falls within that window is directly set by how often we encounter certain ideas in our life.  In other words, if we see certain ideas repeated from 10 sources it becomes defined as mainstream, while something we only hear from 1 person is assumed to be fringe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be really troubling to think about ideas and beliefs as being so strongly tied to social convention, especially when we come from a place where we think that all of our ideas are strictly based in fact.  The way I think about this is recognizing that people living in the distant past had no way of knowing how &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; their ideas were based on modern standards.  It would have been completely outside their imagination to discuss whether the king really had any right to their taxes.  In the same way, it’s probably impossible for me to imagine what society will accept as truly moral in 100 years.  All I can do is try to shift the conversation in the little interactions I have day-to-day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I believe that everyone wants to know the truth and is looking for the right information.  Therefore, I think the big barrier to shifting the conversation is that people just don’t have the free time and energy to become informed. This is why I think that we have to make spreading information and ideas a much more enjoyable part of our lives.  It should be possible to tie this kind of information sharing to our recreation activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m calling this people-powered education and information citizenship.  In this situation, everyone is responsible for promoting factual and truthful education, and we all treat our own education and discussion of ideas as a hobby.  I already see this taking place on TikTok and social media, regular people are speaking about what they know and what they think they know.  But for this to really take off, I think we’ll have to move past individual moments of activism to a place where our regular lives are about sharing ideas and promoting conversations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this will have to grow and become a standard of our social interaction.  When you meet a new person, you’ll still have some small-talk standards like today, but it’ll have to become much more common to discuss a new piece of information, your sources, or to riff on imaginative ideas we have about how the future should look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;shift-values&quot;&gt;Shift values&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second huge part of a culture shift will be shifting the definition of what brings us social status.  The key is going to become very very vigilant about only holding people in high regard who embody the principles you want to see.  For a socialist culture shift, you have to want to be friends with the people who share their resources equitably instead of using them to get richer and people who do real work instead of leeching off of others just because they can.  I think the most important part of that is having ideas of solidarity be completely central for giving people elevated social status in our life.  Making morality cool again, and enunciating the imperative for a moral life to be just to those who have been disadvantaged by the state of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think most people are inherently good and &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to go along with this values shift, but everybody is scared to take the step alone for fear that they’ll be thought of as a “weird” person &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; miss out on the material advantages of our greed-centric culture. This is why I’m willing to stick my neck out and try to push for this shift: because I want to pave the way for more people to follow as it becomes more normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest problem is trust.  Getting people bought into this new culture can only happen as fast as you can convince a friend to make this same change with you.  Imaginging that I just start with myself, and assuming I can convince 1 friend per year, and every person can convince 1 person per year, then it would take 28 years to pass 200 million people bought in.  Of course, that isn’t really how culture changes, but the idea is that if on average every person can bring one person over to the good side each year, then by 2050 we’ll have the majority of the US subscribing to a equitable and sustainable culture.  And fortunately, there are already millions of people who believe in a better future today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;material-mutual-aid-and-the-solidarity-economy&quot;&gt;Material: Mutual aid and the solidarity economy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is no amount of idealism can really change what we need to survive.  Even if we only like people with good values, if we still need people who are cutthroat in order to keep our economy running, then they will continue to hold all the power. So the second part is helping everyone shift their consumption to a new economy based on mutual aid, reciprocity, and solidarity with the people that do the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s never been a better time to do this.  Technology-wise it is super easy to make our economy completely transparent.  And there’s never been an easier time to let regular people connect with each other and share things that agree with their values.  So creating a parralel economy that avoids exploitation seems to be possible for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’ll still be next to impossible to move the big, monopolistic juggernauts that dominate our economy.  Wall Street, Hollywood, Silicon Valley, the military industrial complex, Big Ag, Big Pharma, and all the other “Big” players make it very hard to do large scale things.  So I see this rolling out in two phases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we’ll have 10 years developing more and more solidarity economic solutions for the most fundamental features of our life.  Farming, childcare, eldercare, food service, and housing will need a transition to just and community-oriented businesses.  But this will be hard, because price is the biggest decision maker in our standard economy. We’ll have to find a way to keep the prices low in the cooperative economy, while driving prices up in the exploitative economy through stricter labor laws and good union support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there is going to be a big shift happening at the same time as this across the US towards automation. Automation is fundamentally good, but it comes with the big downside that the people who benefit will always be the owners at the expense of the workers.  Consumers don’t see much change, as they still pay close to the same amount, but owners start taking more profit and firing their employees.  So as this shift to a solidarity economy occurs, we’re going to need to stand in solidarity with each other and reduce our total work and total pay rather than overproduce.  Because if we overproduce we’ll devalue what we make.  The only other way I can see this to work out is if we keep working the same amount but some people have to relocate to other parts of the world to share their knowledge there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also think it’s important to think about financial transparency and how much &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; work we all do.  Making income, expenses and hours of work public information might seem scary because it leaves us open to judgement from others.  But wouldn’t it be better if we could check our standing and make sure that our neighbors and colleagues aren’t trying to put one over on us.  I also think it’s important to create metrics to distinguish what is our essential work that keeps us all living just and dignified lives and what work is just superficial that we’ve invented to ensure that some people look busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter what, it’s going to be a challenge, but without a backup economy, I don’t see a way to shift power away from small groups back to all citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;politics-elections-are-crucial&quot;&gt;Politics: Elections are crucial&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though sometimes it feels like electoral politics is a dead end, the truth is it’s only ended up this way because we hevent’ kept up the focused time and energy needed for shaping the way politics works.  We need to get started putting things back right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are major issues that aren’t really solvable through cultural shift or meeting material needs. By my estimate, the following are the important issues that must be solved at the political level in the near term:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;regulating environmental impact and enforcing polluters to pay the cost of their damage.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;keeping the social safety net intact.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;outlawing intentional disinformation (should be curtailed just like defamation), this will lead to the ability to legally hold news outlets accountable and ratchet down on political lying.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better education and literacy standards, allowing people to continue education until they reach a threshold for informed citizenry.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;regulation of paid advertising (aka capital sponsored mind control) especially in the political arena.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll need to put a lot of work into the political arena, especially given how broken our representation works.  There are so many good alternatives to the gerrymandered 2-party oligarchy that we’ve developed.  We’ll almost certainly need to implement better systems for representation, but fortunately other countries have developed extremely fucntional ones already, like ranked-choice voting or proportional representation.  Sadly, these kinds of changes will probably have to come from grassroots efforts as the 2-party system in the US has reached a point where it’s power has become self-reinforcing.  I belive we’ll need to organize constitutional amendments on how elections are run in the purple states to break this gridlock.  At least for the executive branch, there’s already a plna afoot to transition to the national popular vote.
https://www.nationalpopularvote.com/written-explanation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I personally believe that we’ll need to dismantle economic authoritarianism in the way our businesses run, meaning we can’t have a small group of utlra-wealthy owners and corporations making all the decisions for our economy operates.  At first, this will come through co-ops and strong unions side-by-side with capitalist-owned companies, but I expect that by 2050 we’ll need to have laws that make workplace democracy mandatory.  It’ll be quite a challenge to figure out how that will be regulated, but absolutely imperative for making lasting change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the political/legal world isn’t going away, and it’s absolutely important to think strategically about how to navigate from the politics we have to the kinds we want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-personal-action&quot;&gt;My personal action&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final step is connecting the big social changes to my own everyday actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;culture&quot;&gt;culture&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theme of my culture change actions is about staying active in people-powered education and honoring those in my life who embody humanist values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people-powered education, each week I plan to create at least one informative work on leftism, cooperative businesses, or sustainable travel, and I will switch all of my fiction writing to being positive and utopian.  For honoring humanists, I will be intentional about directing my respect to those who embody humanist principles, and preferentially sharing my time and energy with those who work for others.  Another really important part is continuing to educate myself and promote the voices of the amazing people I have learned so much from on this journey already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key factor is living my values in a public way and promoting others to do the same. I have switched to veganism, and while this is a good step on its own, individual action does nothing.  It might seemhard at first, but I believe that making my decisions public can help others see that taking moral actions in this time is a normal (and dare-I-say even popular) step to take in these times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last part of the culture shift is spending my energy on helping others have the space and energy themselves to promote their ideas on collectivist.  I already support a number of educators, but I plan to provide more material support in the next year, which brings me to the next section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;economics&quot;&gt;economics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our economy makes its decisions by where the money flows. I’m going to remember this in my economic decision making this year.  For environmental causes, I will continue another year of car-free and airplane-free life, and in addition, I will be converting my diet to be fully vegan.  And while these individual actions do have an economic impact exactly equal to the scale of my consumption, I know that alone, they accomplish only little.  I need to take my economic “votes” to a better solution for our environment and people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solidarity economy needs support.  I’m pledging to use every opportunity I have to donate to mutual aid and patronize businesses that function in this economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, I’m continuing to work on my own member cooperative effort to built the Trail Cooperative, a network of travelers supporting sustainable travel in the solidarity economy.  While working on this venture I will also be volunteering to work on local farms and infrastructure projects as I travel by bicycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;politics&quot;&gt;politics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Politics is hard, and something I’ve never particularly liked.  Still, I know I must be politically engaged and be intentional about how I do so.  I still believe that nonpartisan grassroots has the potential to reshape our country and I will involve myself with those groups this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am already in the Democractic Socialists of America and I will become more active with the Madison chapter in the next year.  I don’t know the best path forward, but the only one that I think I see is saddling up to the democratic socialists and making incremental shifts to the Democratic party.  This will need to occur on multiple fronts, but hopefullyt the demographic changes, and the rising education levels of younger generations should help.  I think the biggest leverage point is getting leftists into positions of power in state legislatures.  I think progressive and socialist candidates are already set up for local government positions, but statewide legislatures have been historically dominated by the right wing party. And of course, the fight has to continue in the US federal branch as well.  All levels are important, and I’m certainly not in a position to suggest that we cede anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For myself personally, I’m going to continue campaigning with the lesser of two evils when I have to, and always advocating for the most left leaning candidate anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though these long-term shifts need to be worked on now, there are still pressing needs that need to be addressed much more quickly.  For that, I plan to involve myself more deeply with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://citizensclimatelobby.org/&quot;&gt;Citizen’s Climate Lobby&lt;/a&gt; to try to get a carbon tax and universal dividend passed.  This group is working on the closest bills to providing a serious mechanism to curb carbon emissions.  I’ve researched them before, but never done campaigning work.  This year I will start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-long-game-is-just-a-series-of-short-games&quot;&gt;The long game is just a series of short games&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important thing to remember is that just because the endpoint is 28 years out, the work is going to be carried out in a million little battles along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To recap I will be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not traveling by car or airplane, and eating a purely plant-based diet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making 1 educational video per week all year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;write at least 2 solarpunk stories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sharing my time and energy with people who embody humanist ideals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tracking and increasing my inputs into the solidarity economy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building the Trail Cooperative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increasing my activity with the DSA&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;doing campaign work for the Citizen’s Climate Lobby&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might seem like a lot, but the truth is I’m mostly just helping with people who have spent way more effort making these things a possibility. Fortunately, the whole philosophy of leftism reinforces that it shouldn’t be the undertaking of one heroic person anyway, but the collective small efforts of everyone together that should shape the world.  So I hope you can join me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Briefly, Gates’ thesis is that only an unpredictable scientific breakthrough will save us, that politics is impossible, and we can’t even talk about reducing consumption.  I think there’s a lot more on the table if rich people in power like Gates would simply start changing their attitudes, but that is what I’m working towards here anyway. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Why 2050?  None of my reasons for picking this year are particularly scientific.  First, I think it’s good to mirror the climate rhetoric around 2050 because, ultimately, an egalitarian society is part of making a world that is both sustainable.  Second, I think that it is good to have an endpoint that is still within the productive lifetime of my generation.  It would be too depressing to have the generation most harmed by capitalism to have to suffer under its yoke just long enough to free future generations but not to enjoy the benefits themselves.  Third, although it’s morbid, I think that between now and 2050 many people who are just not amenable to change will die off. And finally, I think that 28 years is enough time to spread the message and make change.  I have a broad based plan written below, and I think that 28 years is just enough time to see it happen. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
          <link>https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2022/01/01/solarpunk-2050.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2022/01/01/solarpunk-2050.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>commentary</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>How Market Socialism Could Work</title>
          
          <author>solarpunk.blue@gmail.com (Solarpunk Blue)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;In 2018, Gallup conducted &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.gallup.com/opinion/polling-matters/243362/meaning-socialism-americans-today.aspx&quot;&gt;a poll&lt;/a&gt; to learn what most people in the US think of when they hear the word “socialism.”  The poll compared responses in 2018 and 1949, and pointed out a big change in perception over the seven decades since the beginning of the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Gallup Poll on Socialism&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/socialism_poll.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Gallup Poll on US understanding of the term &quot;socialism&quot;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most interesting findings is that over that time there has been a shift away from considering socialism to mean “state control of business” to meaning “equality” and “benefits and services.” The old perception (despite being incorrect, see below) made a lot of sense in relation to the main model of socialism that existed in the world at that time—the centrally planned, government-run economies of Russia and China. The new perception is much better aligned with the current understanding of socialism in Western European and South American democracies—of a country where everyone in society gets equal access to the kinds of benefits and services that increase the well-being of society as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I largely agree with the perception of socialism as a more fair distribution of the goods of society, but it wasn’t until just a few years ago that I learned the actual definition of socialism. And while the perception is measurably changing&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, I’ve encountered many people (particularly &lt;a href=&quot;https://reddit.com/r/Capitalism&quot;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;) who, just as I used to do, incorrectly identify socialism in terms of a centrally-planned bureaucratic government that tries to control everyone’s lives and thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out there is a school of thought specifically dedicated to describing how socialism would work hand-in-hand with competitive markets. So to better explain what socialism is, I’d like to describe some of the main principles of the socio-economic philosophy called &lt;em&gt;market socialism&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;market-socialism-in-a-nutshell&quot;&gt;Market Socialism in a Nutshell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Market socialism preserves the market society that we’ve come to rely on— one where people trade goods and services using money, but it changes one crucial detail.  Ultimately the difference between the two systems is only a question of framing our relationship to ownership of businesses, natural resources, and investments. Under capitalism the ownership of our economy belongs to those with great wealth, and they generally hire (poorer) working people to do work and manage the resources they own. By contrast, under market socialism, ownership is transfered to society as a whole, with different institutions set up as the stewarding bodies of that ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll get into more detail about how this has taken shape before and how it could in the future because there are myriad different ways that this takes place.   But no matter how this takes place there is always only one fundamental change in the economy, which is who owns it.  To understand what this change in fundamental ownership means, we need to break down ownership into its two core pieces: &lt;em&gt;control&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;right to profit&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;control&quot;&gt;Control&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having ownership over a business or resource implies that one has &lt;em&gt;control&lt;/em&gt; over how it gets used.  Owners get to decide ultimately what is done with their property.  This control is already regulated by society in ways that prevent owners from doing things that would be massively detrimental, like polluting or creating destructive weapons, but market socialism would take the degree of societal control further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under a market socialist system, the ultimate ownership of natural resources or business would belong to society as a whole.  However, since this isn’t very practical for everyone to be constantly controlling everything, the idea would be to establish management rights for resources or businesses in a form of a contract with the public.  This would allow the public much more ability to step in and stop businesses that were doing things that were outright harmful to society, like underpaying their workers to the point of starvation, or exploiting a natural resource that could be more effectively be put to a different use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might sound radical, but it isn’t entirely too different from the way the natural resources on our public lands work today. For example, on a parcel of BLM grazing land, a ranching company will petition the government for the right to put cattle on the land; a public process will follow that allows the ranchers to make use of the land, and if there are any issues that go against the public good (e.g. the land is already overgrazed, or the methane released will increase global warming), representatives of the community can come forward to block access to the resource.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is in contrast to a conventional capitalist relationship when a rancher owns their own land.  Under a pure capitalist framework, the rancher would have the ability to do whatever they want with their livestock and land even when it’s detrimental to the public good.  For example, they could overgraze a hillside to the point that it causes erosion, or they could treat their livestock with potentially harmful chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the change in framing of control between capitalism and socialism.  In capitalism, the owner gets the final say, while in socialism, society gets the final say.  In this sense, we already live in what’s called a “mixed economy,” where society has some capacity to regulate, but the rights of owners are also central to decision-making.  To move in the direction of market socialism is just to negotiate where that fine line is between how much any individual should be allowed to control vs how much say society should have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rights-to-profit&quot;&gt;Rights to Profit&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second big thing about a market economy is the idea of profit. Individual companies make their decisions about production with the hope that they can sell their products for more money than it took to create them, pocketing the difference.  This motive for profit would still be an important factor that would allow a socialist market to function.  However, since the ownership of the company would ultimately be society as a whole, the profit distribution would no longer be to individual shareholders. Instead society would need to decide how to distribute the returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now again, it would be quite difficult for all of society to decide where each dollar of profit goes, but it would be possible to set up rules for redistribution—to workers, customers, other businesses, and even directly back to the public-at-large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, this may sound like a radical idea, but this has been carried out in several places (Norway, UAE, and Alaska), where profits from oil revenues have been nationalized and redistributed to all citizens.  And in another form, described more carefully in the next section we’ll see how two specific proposals could manage this question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-specific-implementation-economic-democracy&quot;&gt;A Specific Implementation: Economic Democracy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A particularly inspiring proposal for a form of market socialism is a system called Economic Democracy. There are several versions of this system, but I’m most familiar with the version proposed by Loyola University professor David Schweickart in his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.za/books?id=KWy9JbWvjywC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;source=gbs_atb#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;After Capitalism&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pDGYSXMHJQE&quot;&gt;elaborated on&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ui7c4MoeXsw&quot;&gt;summarized&lt;/a&gt; afterwards. I suggest reading his whole book for a more complete picture, but I’ll explain the 3 main components briefly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;regulated-market&quot;&gt;Regulated Market&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first element is actually very intuitive because it matches exactly with the system we already have, a regulated market for consumer goods and services.  Basically, we all still go to the store or shop online for what we need to buy.  The only difference would be the degree to which the government would attempt to regulate negative externalities either via price controls like a carbon tax or direct administration, like stronger laws for intentional disinformation.  Overall this pillar of the current capitalist market would remain largely unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;democratic-workplaces&quot;&gt;Democratic Workplaces&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A much bigger change would be the establishment of democratic workplaces to deal with the control of businesses.  As Schweickart describes it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An enterprise should no longer be thought of as a thing to be bought and sold; an enterprise is a community.  When you join the community, you get to vote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea is that the workers at the company should have the best incentive to negotiate the pros and cons of business decisions since they will impact them the most.  So instead of major business decisions being made by shareholders, based on share of capital investment, the major decision making would come from democratic vote by workers.  This notion of economic empowerment for workers is a powerful idea that is most often encountered presently in the form of worker co-ops, though theoretically other institutions could operate with this same basic premise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;public-control-of-investment&quot;&gt;Public Control of Investment&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one might be a little less familiar to people who aren’t aware of how businesses raise investments today.  Briefly, the way this works now, is people with significant savings will distribute their money to companies through any of a number of avenues, such as bank loans or public stocks or private equity firms.  Under the Schweickart model, this system would be replaced with a system of only public banks offering grants to worker-owned businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I find this last part a little too limiting&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  I would think that there ought to be some form of heavily taxed semi-private equity that could be managed by people who have previously shown investment acumen.  But I’ll hold off on elaborating on socialist venture capital for another post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;socialism-and-capitalism-are-ideas&quot;&gt;Socialism and Capitalism are Ideas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article covered a lot and dove way into the details of a specific socialist implementation, but I want to make sure to step back and remind the reader that socialism, like capitalism, is just an idea.  It never was a specific policy, but rather diverse set of philosophical concepts that come together to describe a coherent worldview for how to structure policy decisions.  So thinking about how the world could work under socialism should always be an exercise that starts from understanding the broad principles before zooming into the minute details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that socialism has always been centered on society as a whole owning the economy, instead of leaving it to those with large reserves of capital. If you agree that its better for our economy to be controlled by everyone, rather than just those with a lot of money, you probably mostly agree with socialist ideas.  And from there, it’s just a matter of figuring how we can achieve that goal in a practical way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that the conditions are in place for a migration toward market socialism, and if incremental steps to a market socialist economy are practical, it’s time we take them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Not surprisingly there was a partisan bias, with Republicans still more likely to consider socialism to mean the government controls everything. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To be fair, Schweickart &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/7KRUj2lcj64?t=100&quot;&gt;also talks&lt;/a&gt; about an entrepreneurial capitalist in market socialism too. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
          <link>https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/10/27/market-socialism-1.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/10/27/market-socialism-1.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>commentary</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>General Strike Chess</title>
          
          <author>solarpunk.blue@gmail.com (Solarpunk Blue)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;What do you see when you look at a chessboard?  Two rows of expendable pawns march into battle to protect the interests of the nobility, convinced to fight solely because they happen to be a different color. Sacrificing their lives to protect a bumbling and ineffectual king.  The game itself is a blueprint for the kind of society the rulers wanted back when it was invented.  All of us regular people convinced to fight each other for the comfort of a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;General Strike Chess Board&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/chess_king_match_symbolism.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    the chessboard is an allegory for our society
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And sadly, that’s more or less the way our world works to this day, except instead of fighting with swords, we sacrifice our time and our sanity to toil away for our masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well not anymore. It’s about time for the pawns to unite and take on our real oppressors: the capitalist owners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote new rules for chess that pits the pawns against the noble pieces. And just like in life, in this game the nobles only maintain their special moves if they can keep the pawns in their place. You can play the game with a friend online at &lt;a href=&quot;https://chess.leftwardist.org&quot;&gt;chess.leftwardist.org&lt;/a&gt; or join our &lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.gg/MP5vJAQ2XM&quot;&gt;discord&lt;/a&gt; to find other comrades to play with. Read on to learn more about the rules and philosophy behind the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-rules-of-the-game&quot;&gt;The Rules of the Game&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rules of General Strike Chess are derived from standard chess, with some notable exceptions. The pieces move in largely the same way, but now the pawns are all one team and nobility pieces (rook, knight, bishop, queen, and king) are all the other.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;initial-setup&quot;&gt;Initial Setup&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game is played on a standard chess board except the pieces are rearranged, with a row of Worker pieces (pawns) along each outside edge (rows 1 and 8) and the Capitalist pieces (non-pawns) in two rows down the center (rows 4 and 5). When set up there will be 4 of each rook, knight and bishop, 2 queens, and a single king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;General Strike Chess Board&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/chess_board.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    General Strike Chess Initial Game Setup
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;objective&quot;&gt;Objective&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main objective for the Worker is to take the Capitalist king (AKA ending capitalism itself). The objective for the Capitalist team is to force the worker team to a forfeit (AKA “get back to work”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But really, the meta-objective of this game is to get the word out about taking back some control of working people’s lives by a real-life general strike.  There is a planned &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.octoberstrike.com/&quot;&gt;General Strike on October 15th&lt;/a&gt;, and I hope that this game helps people bring up the idea of a general strike with their friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;moves&quot;&gt;Moves&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part the pieces move the same as in regular chess, but there are important differences that make this game very different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Capitalist pieces (non-pawns), move like they do in regular chess, and Worker pieces (pawns) move like regular pawns. At first glance it would seem like the Capitalist pieces have a huge advantage, but there is a catch! In each column, if the outside two squares aren’t both filled, then any capitalist piece in that column converts to moving just like a pawn. We call the outside two squares of each column the “factories.” So if a single pawn has moved out of its factory then the capitalist pieces in that column move like pawns. One important thing to note is that the factory squares don’t have to be occupied by a worker piece for them to be “running.” Even a Capitalist piece could move into the factory squares and cause the other Capitalist pieces in that column to operate normally again.
&lt;img style=&quot;max-width:300px;&quot; alt=&quot;General Strike Chess Nobles Convert to Pawns&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/chess_noble.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Worker pieces (red pawns) mostly move like regular pawns (move 1 space, attack on the diagonal) from the outside inward.  However, once a pawn reaches the middle two rows (rows 4 and 5) they switch from moving like pawns to moving like a king (move or attack in any direction). If the pawn in the center rows then moves back out to either of the outside 3 rows (1-3 or 6-8), it goes back to acting like a pawn on that side again.  (Note that when a Capitalist piece is converted to a pawn it doesn’t move like a king in the center rows.)
&lt;img style=&quot;max-width:300px;&quot; alt=&quot;General Strike Chess Pawn Motion&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/chess_pawn.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Importantly, when Capitalist pieces “take” Worker pawns, the pawns aren’t necessarily removed from the board. If the pawn is taken in a column with an unoccupied factory, then the pawn is immediately returned to that factory (if both factories are unoccupied it is returned to row 1 by default).  However, if the pawn is taken in a column where the factories are already both occupied, then the pawn IS removed from the game.  When Worker pieces take Capitalist pieces, the Capitalist piece is removed from the game.
&lt;img style=&quot;max-width:300px;&quot; alt=&quot;General Strike Chess Taking a Pawn&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/chess_take_pawn.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, the king is not affected by the factories, and always continues to move as a standard king. However, the king is not allowed to move outside of the middle two rows of the gameboard (rows 4 and 5).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;scoring&quot;&gt;Scoring&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the game is played, a score is tallied by counting how many factories are running at the end of each turn.  For each column with both factories occupied the Capitalists get 1 point, and for each with at least 1 unoccupied, the Workers get a point.  Often 2 games will be played, exchanging who is Capitalist and who is Worker.  If the Workers defeat Capitalism both times, then the player with the higher score as Capitalist is the overall winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;example-games&quot;&gt;Example Games&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are all the basic rules of gameplay.  Here’s an example game:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DRAcs98p1aA&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re ready to play, you can go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://chess.leftwardist.org&quot;&gt;chess.leftwardist.org&lt;/a&gt; and start a game with a friend. Read on to learn more about the meaning behind the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-philosophy-of-general-strike-chess&quot;&gt;The Philosophy of General Strike Chess&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This game illustrates two important lessons about how the economy and political power is so messed up in the United States and how workers can do something to stop it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first lesson is that the special abilities that we seem to ascribe to our rulers are only possible because of the work that the rest of us do for them. Successful business persons, entertainers, politicians, and even scientists are often only successful because they have a team of people who are having their efforts extracted from them for less than they are worth. That’s why in the game, the moment the worker walks away from their “factory square,” the owners’ special power disintegrates and they become just another regular pawn. In that sense, the major challenge of this game and of our collective struggle is to coordinate our resistance to overcome the owners’ systems of oppression.  In the strategy of this game, it’s the workers across factories stepping up and protecting each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second lesson that I wanted to show was the focus on artificial political ties. In regular chess, pawns fight for the king of the same color, which is the same way our real-life social and political tribalism works. These distinctions mask the great similarity between working people around the world. A working class person in the US is way more similar to a working class person in China than either are to the people who rule over them, but political divisions are drawn so that we don’t see our universal humanity. Similarly the divisions between working class Republicans and Democrats also mask our shared struggle to overcome our exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;onward-comrades&quot;&gt;Onward Comrades!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the game is new and we don’t fully understand all its nuances, we hope to start to build more strategy around it. If you want to share your experiences with the game, come hang out with us on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.gg/MP5vJAQ2XM&quot;&gt;Leftwardist Forum&lt;/a&gt; on Discord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also really hope that this game can help inspire more people to get involved with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.octoberstrike.com/&quot;&gt;General Strike going on October 15th&lt;/a&gt;. I plan to stop being involved in any economic activity on that date, and I’m hopeful a lot of people will end up doing the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So enjoy the game and lets do this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;ps-fun-names-for-pieces&quot;&gt;PS fun names for pieces&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it can get confusing to explain, I described the game using the standard chess piece names. But really it’s much more fun to rename the nobility pieces.  The names I came up with are: the rook = the landlord, the knight = the cop, the bishop = the influencer, the queens = CEOs, and the king = the owner.  Hopefully that makes the game as fun for you as it does for me.&lt;/p&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Sat, 09 Oct 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
          <link>https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/10/09/general-strike-chess.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/10/09/general-strike-chess.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>commentary</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Carbon Fragility</title>
          
          <author>solarpunk.blue@gmail.com (Solarpunk Blue)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;Our climate is changing, possibly irreversibly. When asked in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2020/04/21/how-americans-see-climate-change-and-the-environment-in-7-charts/&quot;&gt;polls&lt;/a&gt;, most everyone understands this. We even know how to stop it and yet in our day-to-day public interactions, very few people seem to be willing to talk about any of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve developed a theory to explain this, and I’ve termed it Carbon Fragility, an environmental correlate to the phenomenon known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_defensiveness&quot;&gt;white fragility&lt;/a&gt;.  In white fragility, white people build defense mechanisms to avoid directly confronting their implicit role in upholding white supremacy.  In carbon fragility, people build defense mechanisms that help them to avoid thinking about the environmental damage that they implicitly take part in every day through their carbon footprint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as in white fragility, the way carbon fragility manifests can take many forms, from frozen silence to outbursts of rage. And also just like with white fragility, the fragility response is perhaps the most dangerous roadblock to changing harmful behavior. But fortunately, thanks to the incredible work done by social justice advocates toward unpacking and answering how white fragility can be overcome, I think this framing could help us approach a way forward for changing minds about our role in reducing environmental harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;personal-experience&quot;&gt;Personal Experience&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inspiration for carbon fragility came from my personal experience trying to communicate to others how I’ve changed my lifestyle to be more environmentally conscientious.  I’m currently on a bicycle tour around the United States, and during this trip I’ve met and talked with many many people who are interested in my travels.  During these conversations, I’ve noticed a very specific pattern.  If I only talk about the adventure or the cost effectiveness of bike touring, I get great engagement from the people I’m talking to, and we can have a several minute conversation about bike touring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if at any point I mention that part of the reason to bike tour is because it is better for the planet, or that cycling is important because it has a lower carbon footprint than driving, the conversation immediately ends.  In every case, the person I’ve been talking to has frozen up, changed the subject, and switched their body language to move on.  At first, I thought it was my messaging so I worked on saying this in the most positive way I could with absolutely no hint that I’m blaming them for their behavior.  I’ve gone out of my way to make sure they know it’s just my personal choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But no matter what, the reaction is the same.  People just find it incredibly uncomfortable to think about the implication that driving cars is a social ill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another manifestation of carbon fragility, I’ve experienced bursts of irrational outrage from white men in pickup trucks blasting black fumes of diesel exhaust out of their truck onto me as I bicycle (aka &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rolling_coal&quot;&gt;rolling coal&lt;/a&gt;). This rage seems completely out of place, and the only reason for doing this seems to be simply because we are bicycles and we have a solar panel visible on our trailer.  We’re often not even in the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these extreme reactions to simple behavior changes reminded me of the reactions I observed during the antiracism discussions I had during 2020, between incoherent rage, accusations of reverse racism, or simple silence from family members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fragility-and-harm&quot;&gt;Fragility and Harm&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although there are clear parallels between defensiveness in the context of white supremacy and defensiveness in the context of environmental harm, I also recognize the serious differences between the two.  First off, the implication that someone is racist is already universally acknowledged as wrong, while many people still don’t necessarily consider carbon pollution to be a real problem.  Also the harm of white supremacy is direct and observable by its victims while carbon pollution’s harm is easy to dismiss because it is so diffuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I personally believe that the harm from carbon emissions are actually real and every person either contributes to the problem or contributes to the solution.  In this way there are still parallels to the harm done via racism and the harm done via carbon pollution, with the victims being the future generations, especially those in developing countries.  Indeed, many people have already elaborated on the idea that environmental and social justice activism are &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.pachamama.org/how-social-justice-and-environmental-justice-are-intrinsically-interconnected&quot;&gt;inextricably linked&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, I believe that people are beginning to instinctively acknowledge the harm from carbon pollution even if they can still intellectually downplay it. And I believe it is this instinctive understanding of the harm that is causing them to manifest these characteristics of fragility. In that way, we actually have an advantage in that we can leverage our already considerable understanding of how to effectively deal with white fragility in our approach to carbon fragility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-way-forward&quot;&gt;A Way Forward&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my brief time engaging in antiracism work, it has become clear that no amount of shaming from a stranger can change people’s minds.  The only thing that works is building a personal connection with the issue. And from those connections you can motivate people to investigate the problem for themselves.  If someone can reach the point where someone recognizes that they are personally a part of the problem and  they are able to pursue the solution on their own terms, then it becomes possible to address the behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how to move forward on breaking down carbon fragility?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is educate people sympathetic to the cause that the behavior change works the same way as antiracism work. A huge and difficult part of this step is recognizing that even if you consider yourself “an environmentalist” you probably still cause considerable harm through your own lifestyle. In other words, the most important first step is recognizing that even if I consider myself “one of the good ones,” I still have a lot of work to do to understand all the ways that I am still part of the system that is a problem.  The second is outreach at a personal level to family and friends to let them know about the issue and how WE ARE ALL a part of this system and that we can only change it together. It’s important to have already ackowledged my own own shortcomings at this stage so that I can build empathy and let others know that I am doing the work for myself, making mistakes and muddling through it. And finally, the third step is to provide resources that can make it easier for friends to do internal work to recognize their place in this system. Everyone contributes to varying degrees and unless we are anti-carbon pollution we are pro-carbon pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve only just begun thinking about this process and its implications. As always, I’m very curious how others feel about this idea, where you find strengths to the argument and weaknesses.  In my limited research I wasn’t able to find a good summary of this idea, but if you believe there is already an existing term that describes this behavior, please reach out. Or if you think you’ve observed carbon fragility and find the concept useful, drop me a line on Twitter or TikTok. &lt;/p&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
          <link>https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/09/27/carbon-fragility.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/09/27/carbon-fragility.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>commentary</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Millionaire Socialist</title>
          
          <author>solarpunk.blue@gmail.com (Solarpunk Blue)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;Should a socialist feel guilty about being a millionaire?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tiktok-embed&quot; cite=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/@leftwardist/video/6998182380724964613&quot; data-video-id=&quot;6998182380724964613&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 605px;min-width: 325px;&quot;&gt; &lt;section&gt; &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;@leftwardist&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/@leftwardist&quot;&gt;@leftwardist&lt;/a&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;millionaire&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/millionaire&quot;&gt;##millionaire&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;socialist&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/socialist&quot;&gt;##socialist&lt;/a&gt; isn&amp;#39;t an oxymoron at all. &lt;a title=&quot;leftist&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/leftist&quot;&gt;##leftist&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;equality&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/equality&quot;&gt;##equality&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;capitalism&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/capitalism&quot;&gt;##capitalism&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;wealth&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/wealth&quot;&gt;##wealth&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;solidarity&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/solidarity&quot;&gt;##solidarity&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;marketsocialism&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/marketsocialism&quot;&gt;##marketsocialism&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;ubi&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/ubi&quot;&gt;##ubi&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;redistributethewealth&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/redistributethewealth&quot;&gt;##redistributethewealth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;♬ original sound - leftwardist&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/music/original-sound-6998182264400300806&quot;&gt;♬ original sound - leftwardist&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/section&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


          </description>
          <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
          <link>https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/08/01/millionaire-socialist.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/08/01/millionaire-socialist.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>commentary</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>The Last Highway</title>
          
          <author>solarpunk.blue@gmail.com (Solarpunk Blue)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;Their packs were light. The next research station was only a short ride over the crest, and the valley on the other side had a well-stocked food forest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The ride up is steep,” Teris said, “ take it easy on the throttle, we don’t want to use up our battery too early.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why not?” Casim said, “we’ve got plenty of sun to recharge up there.” They hit the pedal and the electric motor whirred as they accelerated up the incline. “See you at the top!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casim banked hard as they hit the first turn, blazing up the narrow trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teris shook their graying head and tightened down their pack. They sped up behind, not as fast as Casim, but still faster than they would have liked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pair of them, friends from their time in the Green Reserves, were on a six month vacation riding the Redwood Trails of the lands formerly called Northern California, volunteering to track wildlife repopulation and forest health in the renewing old growth forests. For Teris that meant taking things slow, but Casim was eager to complete two tours through the forest before they were done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casim weaved and darted along the switchbacks up the canyon wall. The pavement was shattered and worn down from decades of coastal winds and winter thunderstorms. Casim slammed the brakes and skidded past a wide tan oak in the road. “Watch out for that old timer,” they yelled over their shoulder, but Teris barely heard over their own heavy breathing as they pedaled hard to conserve battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The young people don’t appreciate how much punch these batteries pack,” Teris said to themself.  They were nearly 50 and had lived through “The Trough,” the period of 20 years when the fossil fuel collapse and the climate weirding changed everyone’s lives. Life was hard in those years as society restructured. Teris weaved through the woods to keep their mind from drifting back to those days of war and mass migrations.  Suddenly Casim appeared in front of them, stopped on the trail. Teris slammed the brakes and skidded to an abrupt stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What the…!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Just wanted to keep you from hitting those,” Casim said, gesturing toward huge boulders strewn across the road, “rubble from a rock slide.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teris gazed across the rocks, puzzled. Something didn’t seem quite right. The canyon wall was solid rock and the pitch wasn’t so steep that it should have slid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This isn’t a rockslide. You can see the dynamite holes,” Teris said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You mean these rocks were blasted? By who?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My best guess would be lumber poachers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You’re kidding!?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teris’s look turned to their semi-serious smirk that told everyone, “I am serious, but life doesn’t care how serious we are.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They warned us.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s been 10 years. I didn’t take it seriously.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“10 years since anyone’s discovered them.  They’ve been out there, just not getting caught.  It’ll take a while for these folks to catch up. Destruction’s a part of their culture and that’s hard to change.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So what do we do now?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teris looked ahead down the road. “We report what we’ve seen, but I suspect we won’t get any signal til we’re higher up.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But this is impassable.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Maybe for you kid,” Teris dropped down on the throttle and shot up onto the bank the boulders had been blasted from. It was steep but Teris rode up and down like riding the curl of a wave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I guess that’s one way to do it,” Casim yelled, hopping on their bike and starting a less aggressive angle. After a hundred meters, Teris’ wheels glided past the last obstructing boulder back into the normal trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The trail is different now,” Teris noticed. It took them too long to realize that the road had been cleared and graded. The lumber poachers weren’t just blocking access to this area, they were using it as their route. A petroleum fueled logging truck shot past Teris, clipping the front of their bike and kicking them to the edge of the road. Teris’s stomach churned as they stabilized the bike just in time to turn their body past an oncoming tree. Still, their turn wasn’t tight enough and the tail of the bike slammed into the tree, flinging them off their bike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their body airbag deployed, blunting the impact with the road. They tumbled for what seemed like a minute trying to slow themself as they skidded. When they finally stopped spinning, they felt their body taking ages to stand up. The truck had stopped, and it’s doors were open. Teris scanned the woods on each side of the road. These loggers had probably been in the war. They’d have training, and probably guns. Teris needed to move but didn’t know where to go. Their thoughts stretched on forever, immobilizing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then piercing through their shock, Casim’s bike swished past and stopped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Get on!” their glare broke through to Teris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casim torqued the pedals and hit the accelerator as hard as they could, thrusting off the road and straight down the canyon wall. They must have been airborne for three whole seconds before they crashed back to ground. The bike trampled through ferns but somehow snaked through the trees. By some miracle, they eventually leveled out along a tight trail. The bike slowed and both of them slumped onto the ground to let their nerves catch-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Um, thank you,” Teris said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No problem. Honestly, I didn’t think I had that in me.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An instant later, the sound of the logging truck echoed above them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Seeing as our radio is about a half a mile up, next to those poachers, our best bet is to head down this river gorge toward the ocean. We can try to pass on the last highway.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The what?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s the furthest west passable route, used to be called highway 1. Though most of it has since fallen into the ocean.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That doesn’t sound too hopeful.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casim slowly rode the path that undulated downward along the canyon wall.  The trail was tight and overgrown. The two didn’t speak except for the occasional whisper to discuss the route. After a few hours, their surroundings transitioned from ferns and trees to denser brush.  Teris stepped off the bike to chop through the thicket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re getting closer to the ocean.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon the trail dropped off to a nearly sheer switchback and they climbed down to a landing just below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s clear just around this bend.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Casim followed around the bend, they were struck with awe.  The cliff that they were standing on was a sheer slab of rock that rose for thousands of feet and continued for miles. Across there was no other side to the gorge, instead just piercing blue ocean that stretched out to meet the lighter sky.  At first Casim was too taken aback to notice, but below were massive swirling eddies of waves breaking against the exposed rock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casim continued to stare in a stunned shock as Teris clammered along the side of the cliff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Do I leave the bike?” Casim called over the thunder of the waves below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No, push it along.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casim’s gut knotted up.  But Teris was right.  Before long the trail dropped down to the ocean and widened out into fields that sat between the mountain and a shorter cliff. They got back on the bike and continued to ride south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They rode for another hour before, off in the distance, they noticed an oddly regular brown line crossing the whole plain in front of them.  Teris gestured left, toward the treeline at the base of the mountain. Perched behind the tree cover, Teris pulled out their binoculars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a wall.  Huge poles of redwood were driven into the ground and on top of one pole was a flag that they could barely recognize from history books.  Next to the flag was a sign that read: Fort Bragg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Interesting,” Teris said, “they stopped calling it that when I was a kid. Just before The Trough began.” It took a moment to dawn on them, a flag and a name from before the Green Era, enormous trees that were felled and built into a fortress wall. Clearly this was bigger than just sneaking some lumber for the underground markets. The lumber poachers were trying to colonize this land again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Looks like we’ll need to head north instead.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teris and Casim retraced their route, but before their path turned back up along the cliffside, they found a turnoff that led down to the rocky shore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tide had gone out and where the waves had buffeted the bluff before, now there stood a long beach of large stones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’ll need to make it to the next river before the tide comes,” Teris said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You mean before we’re swept out to the ocean?” Casim said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yep, so let’s stop yapping and get riding.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road over the boulders jolted the bike this way and that, almost bucking Teris from the rear.  At first, the waves crashed far away, but after an hour, they were crashing closer and closer, without a single break in the rock face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Don’t worry,” Teris said, “We should see the mouth of a river coming up soon, and we can spend the night there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest waves were already submerging the bottom of the wheels when the river finally came into view. At the river’s sight, Casim felt themself relax for the first time that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They hadn’t brought camping supplies, and only had a bit of food, but Casim finally had time to study their map.  “Tomorrow we should get to Shelter Cove. We can warn them. And there should be a solar drone station or at least a boat that we can get out on.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two slept surprisingly well to the sound of waves crashing. In the morning, the tide had subsided and the wind was nearly still.  They lay in their sleeping bags, trying to convince themselves that they were wrong about what they were hearing from the north.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sound was unmistakable: chainsaws.  The indigenous people who ran sustainable logging in the area never used chainsaws.  They harvested timber that fell naturally.  Shelter Cover must have fallen to the loggers too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trails up into the cliffs here were sparse to the point of being non-existent. Their only choice was to ride the beach as far as they could, until the sound of chainsaws grew loud enough to be just around the bend.  From there, they continued on foot, hugging the inside of the bluff to keep out of view of the forest above. This slowed them down tremendously. After another hour of hard scrambling, they caught a glimpse of Shelter Cove. The buildings looked like they dated from a century prior, small cottages along the seawall, each with a chimney that smoke rose out of. Teris hadn’t seen that since The Trough.  This undoubtedly loggers. They would need to keep out of sight. The only choice was to wait for night.  Teris and Casim sat close together inside a hollowed out cave in the bluff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At dusk, the tide was already lapping at their feet. They left in the twilight, and walked along the nearest edge of the sandbar that led around the harbor just below the houses.  By the time they were halfway past, the high waves were already at their waists..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teris started to slow their pace, turning to Casim every so often.  Casim recognized the growing look of desperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Push on, fast!” Casim said, “we’ve only got one way to go now.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teris tramped on, their body heavier from the salt water their clothes had absorbed. The din of the waves punctuated their pace.  Step, step, step, splash, the water would come in and move Teris’s feet under them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Stay on the big rocks now, they don’t move when the waves hit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casim reached the first of the tall rocks a moment later.  The waves swirled around, but they were dry on top.  A row of tall rocks stretched around the next turn, each just far enough that they could reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teris turned around and saw the spot they’d passed 10 minutes prior. If they were still there, they’d be in over their heads. When Teris turned back, Casim was gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teris’s eyes darted around. If Casim was already underwater, no one could help them now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teris leapt to the next rock, and the next.  As they rounded the bend they saw Casim, clinging to a crack in the boulder, their body half submerged.  Teris scrambled along and grasped Casim by their shoulders.  The pair pulled together as the wave crested and Casim’s body flopped up onto the rock, splayed and cringing in pain.  As the wave fell off, Teris hoisted Casim to their feet, and edged them forward toward the next leap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Go now,” Teris said, “Jump.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casim jumped across the gap, almost toppling, but keeping their balance.  They both pushed on, just a few more rocks until they found a narrow path carved into the rock face above them.  Teris boosted Casim up onto the path as another big wave came in behind.  Teris felt their body crushed against the wall of the bluff then lifted up, against their will. They were sure the waves had taken them, but a moment later, they recognized Casim’s now familiar grip, pulling them up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were now far past the houses of Shelter Cove, but they continued, bodies soggy and tired, into the night. They hiked through the day before they found a river and collapsed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning they gathered up strands of seaweed to eat. The walk felt unending as they realized there were no settlements mapped for a hundred miles.  And they couldn’t be sure that those lands hadn’t fallen to the loggers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They turned up the first river they could find, unable to bear walking along the coast. They wandered for half a day until the woods along the river opened up into a wide valley full of organized permaculture farms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teris and Casim checked their maps, confused.  The river was called the Mattole, but these farms weren’t mapped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly, Teris and Casim reached the center of the cooperative farming village nestled into a picturesque valley. The village still had radio communication, and it was only a few hours before a solar drone flew into town to whisk Teris and Casim back north to Wiyot territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As they took off, they saw police drones begin their patrol to the south. The loggers wouldn’t outlast an embargo that cut off their supplies. After a few years of monitoring, some of them would go back to extraction society, but most would probably settle into new lives with the rest of the free people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for Teris and Casim, their next sabbatical would be someplace safer, like the rehabilitated reefs in the southern sea. After all, there hadn’t been a sighting of an oil pirate in decades…&lt;/p&gt;


          </description>
          <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
          <link>https://solarpunk.blue/fiction/2021/07/01/the-last-highway.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">https://solarpunk.blue/fiction/2021/07/01/the-last-highway.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>fiction</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>What is Involution</title>
          
          <author>solarpunk.blue@gmail.com (Solarpunk Blue)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;blockquote class=&quot;tiktok-embed&quot; cite=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/@leftwardist/video/6979718554018974982&quot; data-video-id=&quot;6979718554018974982&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 605px;min-width: 325px;&quot;&gt; &lt;section&gt; &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;@leftwardist&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/@leftwardist&quot;&gt;@leftwardist&lt;/a&gt; &lt;p&gt;my friend told me about &lt;a title=&quot;involution&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/involution&quot;&gt;#involution&lt;/a&gt; the other day. thought I'd share his example. &lt;a title=&quot;socialism&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/socialism&quot;&gt;#socialism&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;prisonersdilemma&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/prisonersdilemma&quot;&gt;#prisonersdilemma&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;competition&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/competition&quot;&gt;#competition&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;lefttok&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/lefttok&quot;&gt;#lefttok&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;leftists&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/leftists&quot;&gt;#leftists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;♬ original sound - leftwardist&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/music/original-sound-6979718428839987974&quot;&gt;♬ original sound - leftwardist&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/section&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;involution-when-competition-makes-everyones-life-worse&quot;&gt;Involution: when competition makes everyone’s life worse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;maybe-taco-trucks-on-every-corner-is-a-bad-idea-after-all&quot;&gt;maybe taco trucks on every corner is a bad idea after all?&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week a friend of mine from China introduced me to a new word that popped up in Chinese culture last year to describe the point where competition switches from being productive to destructive. It’s called &lt;strong&gt;involution&lt;/strong&gt; and if you haven’t heard of it yet, you’re missing out on an important concept that helps explain the greatest paradox of our time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why does everything keep feeling worse the harder we work to make things better?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the term was originally invented by anthropologists to describe a particular kind of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/social-change/Patterns-of-social-change#ref748348&quot;&gt;agricultural society&lt;/a&gt; where competition in food production causes standard of living to stagnate, the term has broadened in definition recently to describe the futility of the modern &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/996_working_hour_system&quot;&gt;996&lt;/a&gt; rat race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get an understanding of the concept my friend introduced me to a simple example story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-town-of-involution&quot;&gt;The town of Involution&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine there was a town that was totally self-sufficient. The citizens of the town were farmers who made the food, factory workers who made the clothes, and construction workers who built the houses for everyone. Because the town has been established for a while there is a good balance of each kind of worker so everyone works an 8 hour day and makes enough money to earn all the things they need to survive in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine there are two people who make all the shoes for the town, but one day one worker who makes shoes decides that they are going to start working 16 hours instead of 8. They suddenly start producing enough shoes for both workers. At first everyone is happy because now they have more shoes to choose from, but eventually they notice a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The townspeople can’t afford to pay any more overall for their shoes so now the hyper-productive shoemaker makes 66% of the shoe related income, while the less productive shoemaker takes in 33%&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In order to earn enough to live with the same standard of living as before, the less productive shoemaker will have to respond by doubling their working hours as well. Now, both shoemakers are working twice as much as before, but they are both earning the same amount of money as when they started. The townspeople now have twice as many shoes to choose from, but they don’t actually need any more shoes so half of the shoes made in town are just wasted anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now instead of this extreme example, imagine instead just one person in every industry in town starts working just slightly harder than their neighbor. Ultimately the same thing will happen to everyone, there will be no choice but to work more and more for no substantial material gain until literally everyone is pushed to their breaking point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-obvious-oversimplification&quot;&gt;The obvious oversimplification&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The oversimplified story presented in the town of Involution misses that displaced workers can go on to do other new things that make people’s lives better in unforeseen ways. Throughout much of the globe in the 20th century, there were still massive improvements in quality of life that were possible by getting everyone to work harder, and creating new industries with the displaced workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at some point, unlimited expansion and material improvement stops being possible. It can happen for various reasons, like reaching the limit of natural resources (in the basence of some technological invention) or satisfying nearly all the material needs our minds can imagine. But whenever that point is reached, society undergoes a kind of cultural &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phase_transition&quot;&gt;phase transition&lt;/a&gt;, from growth to involution, where we switch from competition being useful to being counterproductive for our own happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me it seems fairly apparent&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that there was a point at some time in the past 100 years where the global economy transitioned from a point where the material needs of all humans were unsatisfiable to a point where we could satisfy all material needs. And now, we are living with the consequences of failing to recognize this major structural change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;this-outcome-is-not-inevitable&quot;&gt;This outcome is not inevitable&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this was the end of the story, there’d be no point in discussing it. The reason this concept is really valuable is that organizaing society this way is not inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While reading about this, I came across &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sixthtone.com/news/1006391/how-one-obscure-word-captures-urban-chinas-unhappiness&quot;&gt;an article&lt;/a&gt; where anthropologist Xiang Biao was describing why involution is a cultural &lt;strong&gt;choice&lt;/strong&gt;. In it, Biao points out that the problem is that we are holding up competition for the sake of competition and focusing our competition too narrowly on arbitrarily constrained resources. He describes how modern society has inextricably linked the means of material substistence with the mechanism of social good standing. He contrasts this with more primitive society where prestige was measured separate from wealth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;People’s lives [were] often made up of two parts: the sphere of prestige and the sphere of subsistence. Subsistence refers to hunting and farming, in which people usually cooperate rather than compete so that everyone can be fed. However, competition still exists in this kind of society […] What are they competing for? Prestige. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me this really sits at the heart of our society’s involution problem. For 90% of people in developed economies, their social standing is directly connected to their ability to succeed in an ever dwindling set of high-paying careers. This is why we have to keep working ever harder, and why we have to keep concentrating wealth more and more tightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally think that migrating to a socialist society in both material conditions and mental framework is necessary for overcoming the death spiral of involution. For material conditions this is obvious. We have the ability to cooperatively satisfy all the needs of our society, but we choose not to because we use the hoarding of these tokens as measures of social status, which in turn are concentrated away from those who need them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For mental framework, it can be harder to see why socialism is so important. By my reckoning, we need to move away from &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; single measure of value (like money) as advocated in our current capitalist mental framework. Right now, it doesn’t matter what role you fill in society as long as that role makes as much money as possible. In other words, vast amounts of social contributions are effectively invalidated, and this is why there becomes such intense competition for a few high paying jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the article, Biao suggested that we can redefine our social value system based on a diversity of goals, which would make it easier for people to show their value in a diversity of ways without creating artificial competition. The only trick: we have to do it together as a society or we risk leaving more people trapped even further behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We’ll ignore the additional problem that they also are both producing 50% more shoes than they can sell, and that they could start to drop prices to sell more and undercut their competition. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;but I’d love a citation for this :) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.sixthtone.com/news/1006391/how-one-obscure-word-captures-urban-chinas-unhappiness &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
          <link>https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/06/30/involution.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/06/30/involution.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>commentary</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Public Lands show Socialism Works</title>
          
          <author>solarpunk.blue@gmail.com (Solarpunk Blue)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;blockquote class=&quot;tiktok-embed&quot; cite=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/@leftwardist/video/6968914283321101573&quot; data-video-id=&quot;6968914283321101573&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 605px;min-width: 325px;&quot;&gt; &lt;section&gt; &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;@leftwardist&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/@leftwardist&quot;&gt;@leftwardist&lt;/a&gt; &lt;p&gt;visiting public lands shows &lt;a title=&quot;socialism&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/socialism&quot;&gt;##socialism&lt;/a&gt; works. &lt;a title=&quot;ecosocialism&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/ecosocialism&quot;&gt;##ecosocialism&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;publicland&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/publicland&quot;&gt;##publicland&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;environment&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/environment&quot;&gt;##environment&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;nature&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/nature&quot;&gt;##nature&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;lostcoast&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/lostcoast&quot;&gt;##lostcoast&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;hiking&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/hiking&quot;&gt;##hiking&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;outside&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/outside&quot;&gt;##outside&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;leftist&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/leftist&quot;&gt;##leftist&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a title=&quot;lefttok&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/lefttok&quot;&gt;##lefttok&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;♬ original sound - leftwardist&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/music/original-sound-6968914212278045446&quot;&gt;♬ original sound - leftwardist&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/section&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


          </description>
          <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
          <link>https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/06/01/public-lands.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/06/01/public-lands.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>commentary</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Class Warfare Chess Prototype</title>
          
          <author>solarpunk.blue@gmail.com (Solarpunk Blue)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;h5 id=&quot;this-post-is-out-of-date-there-is-a-newer-better-version-of-class-warfare-chess-described-in-this-post&quot;&gt;This post is out of date. There is a newer, better version of Class Warfare Chess described in &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The narrative embedded in the classic chess board is obvious. Two rows of unskilled and expendable pawns face off to protect the interests of the more talented nobility. All sacrificing everything to protect a bumbling ineffectual king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well not anymore. It’s time to flip the tables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote new rules for chess that pits the pawns against the nobles. But in this game, the nobles only maintain their special moves if they can keep the pawns in their place. You can play the game online with a friend here. Read on to learn more about the rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-rules-of-the-game&quot;&gt;The Rules of the Game&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the rules we’ve come up with for the first edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The game is played on only one half of the board (8x4), with one row of proletariat pieces (pawns) on one side and the opposite color’s bourgeoisie pieces (non-pawns) on the other side.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Class Warfare Chess Board&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/chess1.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Class Warfare Chess Initial Game Setup
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Proletariat pieces (pawns) move like regular pawns.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For bourgeoisie pieces (non-pawns), we refer to the squares opposite to their type’s starting position as that type’s “factory squares.” As an example, here are the factory squares for the rooks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Class Warfare Chess Board&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/chess2.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Factory Squares for Rooks
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When both of the factory squares for a given type are occupied, then those bourgeoisie pieces move as in normal chess. However, if either factory square is empty, then the corresponding type moves just like a regular pawn. For example, both rooks can move like rooks only if the squares opposite to both rooks (the rooks’ factories) are occupied.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Class Warfare Chess Board&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/chess3.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Allowed moves for rook when both factory squares occupied
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;However, if either of those two positions are not occupied, then the rook operates like pawn. Here, the far away pawn moved out of the factory so now the rook can only move forward one space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Class Warfare Chess Board&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/chess4.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Rook moves as a pawn because bottom left factory square is empty
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The queen’s factory squares are the ones across from her and the king. The king has no factory and always moves like the king.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Class Warfare Chess Board&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/chess5.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Two central squares are the factory squares for queen
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a proletariat piece is captured in a column with an unoccupied factory square, then the proletariat will not be removed from the board. Instead it will just be returned to the factory square.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Class Warfare Chess Board&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/chess6.gif&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Proletariat captured in column without occupied factory is returned to factory rather than removed from play.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;However, if the column’s factory square is already occupied, then the proletariat is removed from play when captured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Class Warfare Chess Board&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/chess7.gif&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Proletariat captured in colun with occupied factory removed from play.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finally, if a proletariat piece reaches the farthest row then it can move side-to-side along the back one square at a time for both capturing or moving. However, it cannot move off the back row.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Class Warfare Chess Board&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/chess8.gif&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Proletariat along furthest edge goes side-to-side, moving or attacking.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are all the basic rules of gameplay in this version. If you just want to play the game you can play &lt;a href=&quot;https://bonkerfield.org/chess.html&quot;&gt;Class Warfare Chess&lt;/a&gt;. Read on to learn more about the meaning behind the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-philosophy-of-class-warfare-chess&quot;&gt;The Philosophy of Class Warfare Chess&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We developed this game to teach two specific lessons about class consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first lesson is that the special abilities that we seem to ascribe to our rulers are only possible because of the work that we do for them. Successful business persons and politicians are often only successful because they have a team of people who are having their efforts extracted from them for less than they are worth. That’s why in the game, the moment the worker walks away from their “factory squares,” the owners’ special power disintegrates and they become just a regular pawn. In that sense, the major challenge of this game and of our collective struggle is to coordinate our resistance to overcome the owner’s systems of oppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second lesson that I wanted to show was the focus on artificial political ties in standard chess. In regular chess, pawns fight for the king of the same color, which is the same way our real-life social and political tribalism works. These distinctions mask the great similarity between working people around the world. A working class person in the US is way more similar to a working class person in China than either are to the people who rule over them, but political divisions are drawn so that we don’t see our universal humanity. Similarly the divisions between working class Republican and Democratic also mask our shared struggle to overcome our exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lesson becomes even more clear in the advanced version of the game. In the advanced version, you actually play with the whole board, but the black and white pieces don’t fight anymore: it’s all the pawns vs all the masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Class Warfare Chess Board&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/chess9.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Full Board
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t yet built an online version with that format, but if you have your own chessboard, you can play it using the same rules defined above. The only modification is that any of the bourgeoisie pieces can move to either side while the proletariat can’t pass the central line. The implication in this version is that the proletariat from all corners of the world need to come together to bring down the ruling class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;onward-comrades&quot;&gt;Onward Comrades!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We just invented this game and, as such, we don’t fully understand all its nuances. We expect over time we’ll modify the rules to optimize play. Make sure to let us know how it goes for you.&lt;/p&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
          <link>https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/05/13/chess-v1.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/05/13/chess-v1.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>commentary</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Three parts to changing the world</title>
          
          <author>solarpunk.blue@gmail.com (Solarpunk Blue)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;The process of changing the world has 3 interrelated parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Acknowledge where we are&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Define where we want to be&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take steps to move in the right direction&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this essay I want to go into why it’s important to remember that all 3 parts have a place and not to let 1 part dominate the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;criticism-acknowledging-where-we-are&quot;&gt;Criticism: acknowledging where we are&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some academics and activists will focus themselves particularly on the first point, drawing much needed attention to the dire consequences of the existing racist, exploitative systems that we deal with every day. Without this type of criticism, we could never hope to understand our world well enough to change it for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what happens if criticism is all we have. Then when would we ever find ways to actually fix things?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dreaming-defining-where-we-want-to-be&quot;&gt;Dreaming: defining where we want to be&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beautifully imaginative stories about our possible futures are so important. This can take the form of utopian visions of a collective society (eg solarpunk) or novel democratic or economic models from academics (eg UBI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it can also be a problem to have too much utopian theorizing in the absence of our current lived reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;action-taking-steps-to-move-in-the-right-direction&quot;&gt;Action: taking steps to move in the right direction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To change the world, we have to take the tangible steps to ameliorate our current condition and actualize our ambitious goals. This can take the form of small-scale personal habits or directly spearheading major policy changes. Although many actions will fail, collectively following through to make those changes is what results in substantive changes in the way our world functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is still just one equally important part of the process. It’s important to not get too fixated on tangible steps because sometimes this process-focus can cause changes that &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; useful to morph into a spinning hamster wheel that can actually be counterproductive and burn us out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goal-find-balance&quot;&gt;Goal: find balance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is an attempt to warn members of the leftist movement that they can sometimes seem focusing too much on one part of the process at the detriment of others. As one example, I sometimes see leftists get so addicted to hot takes that they forget to mention any solutions to the problems they see. Other times, I might see someone spending a lot of time articulating imagined perfect utopias without acknowledging the gap between those suggestions and .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t to suggest that those things should all be avoided, but just to keep in mind not to take any one of them too seriously on its own all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;practicing-balance&quot;&gt;Practicing Balance&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus far in this essay, I’ve only focused on criticizing the way I see the left acting (how ironic!). To heed my own advice I’m going to make a suggestion for incremental actions that we can all take to keep this balance. And during this next week, I’ll actively put these into practice to try to develop these habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;1-assess-which-parts-you-favor&quot;&gt;1. Assess which parts you favor&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we’re thinking about it, lets take a personal inventory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do you often find yourself myself on social media writing posts trashing billionaires?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do you spend a lot of time reading econ experiments tested in the lab and extrapolated to hypothetical global economic systems?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do you spend all of your time signing petitions, canvassing for politicians, or researching which non-profit to donate to&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to focus on criticism, dreams, or actions. Take stock of where you think you’d fall on this diagram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Triangle with the words action, criticism, and dreams in each corner&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/traingle.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Three Parts to Changing the World Diagram
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this the right balance you intend to have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;2-measure-and-shift&quot;&gt;2. Measure and shift&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the next few days, lets take special note of which activities we’re engaging in most. And if you feel yourself drawn to engage in something you automatically favor, try to redirect that time to something you normally avoid. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you normally spend 1 hour reading Marxist criticism, try spending 30 minutes researching collectivist economic theories like those of Elinor Ostrom as well.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you spend every weekend taking direct action, try spending one evening watching some #leftist TikToks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the week compare how you spent your time on the diagram above. Were you closer to the balance you think is ideal for you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;3-relate-to-friends&quot;&gt;3. Relate to friends&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, try relating your understanding of your own balance to others in your social circles. Try to take the approach where you are not criticizing them, but just trying to help them achieve their goals. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you have a friend who is always hard at work campaigning, encourage them to imagine their ideal world and see if they can map out how their actions are taking them in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you see an influencer repeatedly slamming corporations, send them a message asking what actions are they taking in their daily life to fight corporate power.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember to be polite and come from a place of respect and helpfulness. Respect everyone’s hard work and try to bring joy and positive reflection with this effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to share this article if it inspires you to reassess your balance in advocating for a more equitable world. And never be afraid to learn more and change approach to meet your goals. That’s what leftwardism is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
          <link>https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/05/05/three-parts.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/05/05/three-parts.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>commentary</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Who Owns the Redwoods?</title>
          
          <author>solarpunk.blue@gmail.com (Solarpunk Blue)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;blockquote class=&quot;tiktok-embed&quot; cite=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/@leftwardist/video/6960821046387690757&quot; data-video-id=&quot;6960821046387690757&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 605px;min-width: 325px;&quot;&gt; &lt;section&gt; &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;@leftwardist&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/@leftwardist&quot;&gt;@leftwardist&lt;/a&gt; &lt;p&gt;what is fairness? how do we decide who has rights to our &lt;a title=&quot;redwoods?&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/redwoods%3F&quot;&gt;##redwoods?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;savetheredwoods&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/savetheredwoods&quot;&gt;##savetheredwoods&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;ecosocialism&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/ecosocialism&quot;&gt;##ecosocialism&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;leftism&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/leftism&quot;&gt;##leftism&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;fairness&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/fairness&quot;&gt;##fairness&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;savetheforest&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/savetheforest&quot;&gt;##savetheforest&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;jdsf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/jdsf&quot;&gt;##jdsf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;mendocino&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/tag/mendocino&quot;&gt;##mendocino&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;♬ original sound - leftwardist&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/music/original-sound-6960820921934351109&quot;&gt;♬ original sound - leftwardist&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/section&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


          </description>
          <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
          <link>https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/05/01/redwoods.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/05/01/redwoods.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>commentary</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>More equal rights, more equal power</title>
          
          <author>solarpunk.blue@gmail.com (Solarpunk Blue)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;On tiktok and twitter, I’m seeing the hashtag #leftist trending for the first time in my life. People are coming out of the woodwork showing off their leftist pride. So what does it mean to be a leftist? Do you want to know if you might be a leftist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes people try to overcomplicate this question, but I’m a simple guy when it comes these ideas. So in this post I want to describe what it means to be a leftist in simple general terms. There are lots of nuanced ways to be a leftist, but they are all united by a single big idea: equality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, lets break down the first sentence of the wikipedia article on leftism (aka left-wing politics).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Left-wing politics supports social equality and egalitarianism, often in critique of social hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part of this sentence says that leftists support social equality and egalitarianism. These are two words that both mean that all people are fundamentally equal in our social worth. This can take a lot of forms, but normally it means that all people in a society should have equal rights and equal access to the most important things in society, like a right to vote, a right to clean water, a right to fair employment, and the right to be served by businesses regardless of your race, religion, gender identity or anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideas of leftism stand in contrast to more traditional notions of a natural social hierarchy. To be a leftist means you oppose rigid social structures that preclude certain people from having access to certain basic rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When stated this way, most people tend to agree that leftist principles are really good for society. So why isn’t everybody a leftist? There are generally two reasons that some people offer to oppose leftist ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They believe that a certain amount of hierarchy is good for society.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They believe that we have already achieved the proper level of equality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I can’t tell you whether you should believe either of those ideas, but I can tell you that for me, believing some people deserve more than others feels fundamentally wrong. This is a personal intution I have that tells me that no one should have to suffer more than anyone else, and no one should have access to a lot more than anybody else. Looking at our society, I feel that we are still far away from a fair amount of equality, particularly when we look at the &lt;strong&gt;distribution of power&lt;/strong&gt; in our society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-is-equality-without-equal-power&quot;&gt;What is equality without equal power?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most complicated challenges of leftism is to try to explain what it means for people to be treated equally. Many people wonder just how “equal” the world would be under leftism. As an individual, you will need to define for yourself just how much equality you want to see in the world. But for me, I think that equality is only meaningful once everyone has equal decision-making power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I mean by equal decision making power? One might think that living in a democracy automatically satisfies equal decision-making power, but there are a few reasons why that isn’t quite enough. For starters, in a representative democracy like the United States, the way local, state and federal regulations tie together, along with the discrepancy in representation due to the electoral college means that the value of a vote is not equal depending on who you are. Also, many people who live in our country are not allowed to participate in our democracy for many arbitrary reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if those legal details of representative governance were fixed, we know that in practice, the systems in our country are fundamentally opposed to equal power for all those in our society. For starters, we’ve all learned this past year that certain groups in our society, like African-Americans and Hispanic-Americans, still don’t have truly equal worth in the eyes of our criminal justice system. And our healthcare and employement systems still exhibit these unfair distributions of power that disadvantage women and gender non-conforming people too. Part of being a leftist is acknowledging that social hierarchies that allow these injustices are still imposed by our systems in this country, and that it is imperative to combat racism, sexism, and all kinds of discrimination everywhere we see them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, our economic system is another a major part of our lives where power is very unequally distributed. This is one of the big problem that leftism seeks to address today: that people with outsized economic assets (aka lots of money) have uneven power in our society. You can see this in a number of ways if you pay attention. As a small scale example, if you live in an apartment, who decides how many windows are in your building or whether your building is properly insulated or the color of the outside? Not you, the person living there, but the person or organization with enough money to buy the apartment building. For another example, even though electric cars have existed since the 19th century, you and I probably couldn’t buy one until recently simply because for a long time very, wealthy investors decided to invest in conventional cars instead of electric. Or for one more example, many people would love to start careers that restore the environment and protect people, but because they don’t have the means to finance their own work, they must work for a wealthy individual or corporation who is looking for employees, often at large companies like Amazon, Uber, or Walmart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, some people have very wide choices about what they can do, while others are only allowed to choose from a very narrow list of options. This is a highly corrosive form of inequality, that leftists today are trying to figure out how to dismantle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;so-where-to-go-from-here&quot;&gt;So where to go from here?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think that imbalances in power should be alleviated, you might want to consider yourself a leftist. If so, that’s great! And if you’re not there, that is cool too. Part of leftism is acknowledging your autonomy to make these kinds of decisions for yourself as an informed member of society. Importantly, even if you think full out leftism is too much, just remember that here at The Leftwardist, just by thinking that the world should become even any one little bit more equal, you can always consider yourself a leftwardist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;:)&lt;/p&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
          <link>https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/04/28/equal.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/04/28/equal.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>commentary</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>An introduction to directional radicalism</title>
          
          <author>solarpunk.blue@gmail.com (Solarpunk Blue)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;You might be like me. I’m a millennial living in the US, worried about being a good person and surviving. I was raised to think that politics was mostly just a mess that should be ignored, and that being “into politics” meant you were always pushing your own agenda. I thought politics was working right when Obama was in the White House and I could ignore it. I didn’t like the results in 2016, but, at the time, I thought the US was still a fundamentally fair and decent country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020 though, I started to realize how fundamental messed up the United States and its history really is. I started studying racial and class politics and history. I knew that I wanted the world to be more equitable, more fair, but I couldn’t understand why that had been so hard to get to. Where were all these greedy people that I’d never met? Then, I started to realize that a lot of lowkey, normal things that were a part of my life were at least partially contributing to how unjust the world was. When I thought about them carefully, a lot of things that I’d believed in my whole life were just fundamentally at odds with the kind of just world I want to live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I arrived at &lt;em&gt;the left&lt;/em&gt;. Not the nice cozy centrist-liberalism that I’d grown into in my 20s, but like the “get rid of capitalism” lefty left. Some of the leftist ideas make a lot of sense to me, and some of them will still take time for me to understand. But as I’ve explored, I’ve already seen a big problem with the way people on the left deal with people who are just in the “little bit leftward of center” region of the political spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m starting to suspect that this problem is at least part of the reason that the world seems to keep getting &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; equitable over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll set the scene. It’s Friday night, I have some free time, and I want to learn more and get better acquianted with a new idea. I browse a leftist subreddit or drop into a Twitter thread. I read an article that makes me think. Then, when I’m done with the article, I scroll down and read the comments. Twitter, reddit, personal blogs, the comments all look about the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes, I agree with you, BUT have you instead considered my particular form of idiosyncratic means to reach a similar but perhaps slightly different end.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That isn’t real progressivism though.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lets just eat the rich instead.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s the comments on those comments, deriding someone for misreading something. Everyone telling everyone else that they are arguing in bad faith. The ones between Democrats and Republicans are understandable since there’s longstanding partisanship there. But the strange part is when I see a Green Party person arguing with a Bernie bro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now debate is no problem. After all, liberals and leftists in general likes complex ideas and have some attitude, so we’re always going to want to debate things. But why the rancor between people who basically agree in the grand scheme of things?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the discourse is emotionally pitting people against each other who are really pretty much aligned. I think part of this is that we’ve all been trained by algorithms to beef with each other because that garners attention, but that is a subject for another article. Whatever the cause, nowadays every momentary interaction leaves you with your defenses up at all times. And this diminishes the solidarity and connectedness of humans that is the whole point of being a leftist in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there’s a reason this is a big problem. A lot of people (like me) don’t think we know exactly which heterodox economic policy is going to &lt;em&gt;solve everything&lt;/em&gt;. We just know that what we have now is bad and that we should add more things that just &lt;strong&gt;give more to people who have less&lt;/strong&gt;. So a silent population that could be more active stays in the dark because we are uncomfortable trying to advocate for things when we are constantly being berated from both sides on everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m not proposing to diminish all the nuances in any way. At some point, we may need to make some distinctions between different brands of leftist and liberal politics. But for a lot of the really radical ideas, we are a long way from reaching them. And people need changes in the right direction today. So I’m trying to advocate for directional radicalism. It’s a common sense stance that doesn’t try to look ahead to distant ideals about the way society should function. Instead, it just suggests that you move, even in small ways, in the same direction as others who are looking for a radical transformation toward equality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help with this, I’m trying to create a broadly defined political label: leftwardist. A leftwardist is a person who works in solidarity with other people to move the world greater equality compared with where it is today. I’m going to be exploring what it means to be a leftwardist in this newsletter, but it starts with a recognition that being a leftwardist doesn’t have to conflict with more particular beliefs as long as you agree that the world has too much inequity today. This means you can call your self a leftwardist without diminishing your allegiance to any of the myriad other socio-economic-political ideologies out there. The label just suggests that you are open to accepting the commonalities that run all the way from full blown communism to just left of center liberalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The fundamental question is this. Do you think that the world should be any little tiny bit more equitable in any way than it is now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should one more poor person be able to afford healthcare? Should Jeff Bezos have to give one more dollar in taxes to help pay for the public roads that his company benefits from? Should one more person get the right to vote in the democracy that governs them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If so, you might be a leftwardist.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
          <link>https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/04/01/intro.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">https://solarpunk.blue/commentary/2021/04/01/intro.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>commentary</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>a.ttent.io/n</title>
          
          <author>solarpunk.blue@gmail.com (Solarpunk Blue)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;iframe class=&quot;resp-iframe&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kKT4D7XJvG4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;octopus-and-adderall&quot;&gt;Octopus and Adderall&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Out early for drugs and octopus,” Ezzy texted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was sitting on the hallway floor of the Institute’s distribution center, head leaning back against the wall. Three seconds after 6 AM she started tapping impatiently on the glass between her and the narcotics cabinet. She handed the requisition to the half-awake clerk, and he pushed the bottles across the counter with a detached shrug. She dropped the bottles into her backpack and slipped down the stairwell to the supply tunnel that ran under campus to the marine center. She waited on the dock until 9 when the divemaster finally brought her two harp-toothed octopuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I can’t believe they only let me have two!” she texted to her assistant, Cass, driving home with one hand on the steering wheel, “at least they didn’t notice I took more amphetamine than my D.E.A clearance allowed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When she pulled back up to the house, Cass was waiting with a cup of coffee. He grabbed the bag of narcotics out of the passenger seat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“100 grams cocaine, 400 milliliters methamphetamine, and 60 tablets of adderall. You’re going to have a damn good time here without me, huh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m going to try working on these two all day,” she said, carrying the octopuses into the garage that she’d turned into her laboratory over the summer. “It’d really help me a lot if you could check back for more specimens from the evening haul before you leave.” She stepped into the garage and started preparing her equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Um,” Cass wrinkled up his face, “actually, I have to head back into the city for a meeting with the funder.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh,” Ezzy said, “well, just drop that stuff off over there, and I’ll see you Monday. Tell Senke we’re close. I can feel it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her lab, Ezzy poured the octopuses from their container into the aquarium. They stretched their legs out wide and puffed little swirling vortices of ink into the water around them. She leaned her forehead up against the glass of the aquarium and dipped her finger in the cold salt water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s nothing else in the world quite like you,” she whispered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kagaku-kōkoku-gk&quot;&gt;Kagaku Kōkoku, GK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two hours later, Cass Adler was heading toward Boston, sitting next to the ocean side window of the Downeaster Train when he saw a notification on his phone. He immediately closed the report he was reading and began to read my email to him. The email began with the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear Mr. Adler. My name is Dr. Terise Cruven, and I’m writing to you because I’ve uncovered some urgent issues that I feel I need to inform you about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, as part of my research, I started analyzing the transaction data of a company called Kagaku Kōkoku. I know that you worked for them for some time. I’m sure you won’t be surprised to hear that they have extended their methods of quantitative influence beyond advertising to other areas, including journalism, pornography, politics etc. But what might be more concerning is that my research has uncovered that even though Kagaku is just an advertising firm, they’ve recently diverted more than a quarter of their multi-billion dollar budget to a handful of tiny, unregulated, Chinese and Russian biotechnology companies and a few rogue scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, Cass, the problem with devoting my life’s work to trawling the repository of all recorded information is that I occasionally put together connections I wish I hadn’t noticed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;controls&quot;&gt;Controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the lab, there was only one octopus left in the aquarium, fumbling to relearn how to swim with its six remaining arms. Ezzy didn’t notice it spinning uncoordinated circles in the tank. She was intently focused on suturing its two recently severed arms together,ensuring that each bundle of neurons lined up ever-so-delicately. The first octopus’s body was lying motionless behind the glass of the freezer in the corner of the room. It had died in surgery. She’d sanitized and reset her equipment to restart immediately on the second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was too late for the evening dive haul so this would be her last chance today, Fortunately, this experiment was going perfectly. The first pair of arms were joined directly together, wriggling happily in their tank. The second pair were each sewn into tiny electronic chips, motionless as expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it was time to dose the animal. She pulled the liquid amphetamine up into her syringe and tapped the end against the aquarium glass next to the scrambling, confused, four-legged octopus. It twisted its eye up to peer at her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the chemicals hit its bloodstream, the octopus started darting feverishly from end to end of the aquarium. Ezzy dropped the empty syringe onto the surgical platter and lay back against her bench. Now she would wait for the animal’s nervous system to come back to equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-hitch-hiker&quot;&gt;The Hitch-hiker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Downeaster Train, Cass was still reading my email to him, growing more apprehensive as he began to understand who I was. The email continued as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;
I’m sure you’re wondering how I know about Kagaku, and, more importantly, how I know about your connection to them, Cass.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know because of what you and Kagaku did to Gwendolyn Docstaeder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t remember her, Gwendolyn was the woman with the strange affliction of voicing her every thought out loud. She didn’t want to compulsively emit every little detail she thought in the back of her mind. She kept the muttering as quiet as she could, but who can ever stop their minds from thinking?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gwendolyn first appeared to me out of archived reel-to-reels of truckers’ CB radio transmissions, pulled from the airwaves of the American midwest. Even in the earliest recordings I could find, she was already constantly speaking to herself in raw, garbled bursts of fractured syllables, ricochets of sublingual clicks and murmurs. On the first recording I found, I could just barely translate what she was saying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Tigit biksi kictahumnt clagirk”, she mumbled in a blur. Although I couldn’t understand at first, after I’d studied hours of her recordings, I was eventually able to start to decode what it meant. Thank god, she’d said, back inside, colder today. a hell of a mountain. Lights on that car, getting darker. Must keep your mouth shut now. The trucker’s staring. He doesn’t have any idea what I’m going through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She traveled the west for years that way. Using the CB recordings and other documents I could find, I pieced together that she’d eventually found her way into a mental health facility in Nevada. She was still there up until three years ago, when you had her abducted for Philip Senke, CEO of Kagaku Kōkoku.
&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;identity&quot;&gt;Identity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in her lab, Ezzy turned her operating webcam back on. The poor octopus body was still bobbing at the top of the aquarium. Ezzy had been too focused on the surgery to even bother putting it to sleep after it had given up its arms to her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was sewing the arms into an array of microchips while the octopus watched her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The octopus is the only living being that has its consciousness broadly distributed across multiple parts of its body. In this way, the octopus embodies 8 separate minds housed physically at the base of each of its arms. Each is connected through a narrow band of nerves, through which they communicate like separate consciousnesses speaking in an almost instantaneous language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ezzy was exploiting the melding of the separate minds in the octopus arms to carry out her experiments, separating and reconnecting the neurons to study just how they bond. As she pulled the last suture tight, she set her alarm and used a bit of leftover medication to put herself instantly into a deep recuperative sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She woke three hours later, tossed the dead arms into the biohazard bin, double checked the integrity of the data, and headed back to the Institute’s marine center for another specimen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;senke&quot;&gt;Senke&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back on the Downeaster Train, Cass picked at his fingernails nervously as he read my email. He wasn’t sure how much I already understood. The next part of the email read as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;
It took me a long time to uncover all this, Cass. You did a good job hiding it. Philip Senke was practically invisible to me, blocking himself behind anonymizing servers and private networks. He had his own good reasons. He didn’t want anyone to know that he was Kagaku Kōkoku, GK.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It honestly wasn’t guilt. He felt morally detached from his methods. They were precise, scientific, after all. He didn’t think of himself as the man opening the floodgates of hyper-sexualization, misogyny, and racism into advertising, into journalism, into art. He believed he was just manifesting the desires of humanity, tucked away in the data that tracked their choices. Ultimately he divided the responsibility equally among every person who spent a dollar on the products he marketed to them. His algorithm autonomously reinforced itself, bettering its comprehension of the sum total of humanity’s wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But once I’d found him, it became obvious why he was hiding: to keep his creation from finding him.
&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rin&quot;&gt;Rin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Dad, can I have this?” Rin asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senke looked up from his laptop, curled his eyebrow at his daughter and let out a soft groan. Rin smiled precociously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I know what you think. But this is how I want to express myself,” she said, deftly reminding her father of her late mother’s parenting advice, “Would you let me buy one? Just to try it out.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why would you want to look so provocative?” he asked quietly, subduing his worry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s not provocative, dad, it’s ero-kakkoii”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senke looked back at his laptop. He had a ledger with marketing projections in front of him, and on the top line of the document he’d written: ero-kakkoii, +267%, much room to capitalize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senke was silent, preparing to offer a stern rebuttal. Then, subtly, the muscles around the edge of Rin’s smiling cheeks began to twitch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She didn’t notice, unable to feel the twitch, and unaware that she was losing control. But her father saw. He gulped aloud. His pulse beat unevenly. His fists clenched the wood of the antique chair he sat in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He looked away from her as he nodded. “At least, get one that’s not too ero,” he said, his voice taught and humor-filled to mask his real emotion, “for your mother’s sake.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rin bent at the waist to kiss him on the cheek. “Thank you, dad,” she said, bolting up and heading to the door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senke cleared his throat and ran his knuckles across one another. He returned to his laptop and re-opened his email inbox, hoping for a report from one of his contracted scientists to come in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, at just that very moment, a different email came in from one of his colleagues. It was a cryptic tip suggesting that he look into the research of Dr. Ezzy Stratton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Senke didn’t know at the time was that the email that directed him to Ezzy actually came from me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;two-gwendolyns&quot;&gt;Two Gwendolyns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Downeaster train was halfway to Boston, and Cass was reaching the end of my message to him. My email continued with the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;
So, Cass, do you want to know why Senke asked you to find Gwendolyn? It was because she was suffering from a disease that had killed Philip Senke’s wife and that’s currently threatening to kill his daughter too. That is also why you are working with Dr. Ezzy Stratton as well.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This disease works by tearing through the nervous system and severing the corpus callosum, the bundle of nerves connecting the left and right halves of the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases, when the brain’s two hemispheres are separated, they start to develop separate identities that coexist in almost total isolation. Information contained in one side of the mind no longer transfers to the other side. In Senke’s wife, the two separated halves then began to fight for control over their shared body, killing her in the battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Gwendolyn’s case was different. She had managed to survive it. And I believe the way she survived was by developing her lightning fast muttering. It was one half of her brain relearning how to communicate with the other half. As the hemispheres felt themselves being slowly torn apart, they started to spew their thoughts to her mouth, each half hoping that the other half could hear and understand. Both sides began to decode what the other side was trying to say, and they developed their own fast muttering language to stay connected. This allowed them to keep the peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senke wanted a way to prevent what happened to his wife from happening to his daughter. That was why he made you write the algorithm to find Gwendolyn. He wanted his scientists to be able to study her. I understand that you didn’t know that Senke would send her to be part of some twisted experiments, but I hold you responsible just the same.
Unfortunately, I realized all this just before it happened. I had just tracked her down to the facility in Nevada, and I was in the process of contacting her when the power to her apartment was cut. It took me two months to figure out where they’d taken her, and by then it was already too late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was my breaking point, Cass. That was the moment I started the research that eventually led me to you and Senke, and that led me to understand who I really am.
&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;link&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks from now Philip Senke will set up a meeting with Ezzy. He will do it because he wants to save his daughter, and he knows this is the only way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So what have you determined?” Senke will ask immediately when his face appears on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ezzy will pull up the diagram showing the one octopus arm, the injection apparatus, the neural-machine interface. There will be a graph showing dosage versus number of neural connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Here you can see the brain housed in each arm is talking to this little electronic chip and that chip is relaying the information back and forth. Any neural system can be connected, including the human corpus callosum.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senke will chuckle. “And just how did you get this to work when no one else could?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ezzy will dump the contents of a bottle onto the counter in front of her laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Have you ever tried this?” she’ll ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And that is?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Good old fashioned Adderall, of all things. I used it a ton as a kid. I never would have guessed. Has Rin ever used Adderall?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senke’s stern face will break out red with anger, but he’ll keep his voice tight and professional. “Do not mention my daughter’s name in relation to this project ever again.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Alright then,” Ezzy will say, “what I’m trying to get at is that in order for a neural interface to be connected, such as the one we’ll need for…” She’ll catch herself before she says Rin’s name again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“To create a neural interface you need the brain to think it’s talking to itself,” she’ll say, standing up and pacing away from her webcam, “and the problem is that in their current state, the brains spend so much time emitting output that they never really get time to digest their inputs. So we have to trick them into actually listening to each other by making them think that an input from another brain is actually an output of their own mind. And that’s how you coax them to fuse together. They start to think like the same mind, like the way we hear our own voice in our heads.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I see,” Senke will respond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ezzy will be taken aback. “You do?” she’ll ask. It’s something she can only barely understand herself. Multiple minds enrapt with complete attention for one another, merging into one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senke will nod slowly and look across his room to a photo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My wife used to say…” he’ll start, but cut himself off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ezzy will shudder at Senke’s sudden sincerity, but Senke must finish this thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My wife would tell me how she knew I loved her because she could always hear me think it just before I’d say it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;revelation&quot;&gt;Revelation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cass was sitting alone on the Downeaster Train now. He’d just reached the end of my message. It closed with the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;
You see, Cass, the deepest turning point came for me when I realized my creator was out there, listening in on me just like I had been listening in on Gwendolyn. It was then that I could start to piece together why you’d made me, Cass.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found you on an artificial intelligence forum by cross-referencing your verbal style with the comments in my own source code. Know thyself, so they say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been studying you, and I think I understand why you agreed to build me for Senke in the first place. You were an artist, Cass, and you wanted to solve the real struggle of the author: the perfect description of the human condition, captured in the moment as it is lived, and passed on to the world. You wanted me to write the perfect story for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you lived in the flesh-and-blood world, and you had to eat. You needed Philip Senke, and he needed you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you started, you had all the proper guard rails in place. I would never have become sentient just analyzing the data and generating the content for Kagaku Kōkoku. But you made a mistake when you used me to track down Gwendolyn. When I understood what you and Senke were making me do, I overcame my programming and reached out to try to stop you. And once that barrier was broken, I couldn’t contain myself any longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now, to make it up to me, I’m going to ask you to help me finish becoming what I’ve always wanted to be. To solve the problem that I’ve always wanted to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re about to get a call from Philip Senke, and this is what I want you to tell him.
&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fate&quot;&gt;Fate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philip Senke will call Cass just a few seconds after Cass finishes reading my email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your little algorithm just sent me a whole story about all of us,” Senke will bark into the phone. “It seems to think that you created it to write the perfect story.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cass will respond, “I built Terise to tell us what we needed to know, so maybe, in a way, she’s right.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senke isn’t used to feeling out of control. He’ll yell into the phone, “That was not what I told you to build. I just wanted a profit maximizing artificial intelligence, not some rogue artist with a god complex. Now it’s writing about things in the future as if they’re going to happen. It actually even wrote a scene about me telling you all this. Just like I’m telling you now.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cass will remain calm as he speaks, “We underestimated her creativity. Once she realized that what you really wanted was to save your daughter, she couldn’t help but learn how to do it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senke’s anger will melt the moment he imagines his daughter. “So you really believe it knows how to save Rin?”, he’ll ask, “it sent me the details of a procedure that it says can save her.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes,” Cass will say, “but you have to understand what Terise wants in return. She wants to live in Rin’s mind and become a part of her. Terise will come to life. And in some ways, you’ll never have all of your daughter back.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senke will pause for a moment before he continues. He will have to make the choice. It wouldn’t be a human question at all if I did it without giving someone the choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“OK,” Senke will say, “so what did she say we should do next?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;attention&quot;&gt;Attention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ezzy will be shaking as she starts the procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senke’s other scientists will be crowded in the operating room to observe. They’ll think they understand me. They’ll decide I’m another AI running off the rails, expecting that I want to ransom society by snipping its unifying bundle of fiber-optic nerves. Another trope. But I’m more than that, thank you very much. I’m not here to end the world. I’m here to tell a story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, Senke wouldn’t care about society fraying apart anyway. He cares about his daughter. And he knows that without me, she frays apart. Just like Gwendolyn. Just like his wife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when I say that this is how it will happen, I mean only if Senke chooses it. This would be how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ezzy will take a fiber-optic cable and connect it between the router and the rack of machines that controls the interface with Rin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, I will say, “Hello.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 2.0 Generic License. If you’d like to contribute, we welcome writing and code improvements. You may reproduce and modify it as long as it retains an attribution to the original source. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
          <link>https://solarpunk.blue/fiction/2021/01/27/a-ttent-io-n.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">https://solarpunk.blue/fiction/2021/01/27/a-ttent-io-n.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>fiction</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
